第一季第六集
我绝不会心慈手软
There will be no mercy!
《公元》前情提要
我妹妹的独子被钉在十字架上
My sister's only child hanging from a cross!
约瑟  我们需要结束这一切
Joseph... we need this to end!
我们必须依照我们的法律
We must govern ourselves
才可以无需臣服于罗马的铁蹄
so that we are never again subjected to Roman justice.
反正你没做过任何有价值的事
You did nothing of any worth whatsoever.
给希律・安提帕斯王让路
Make way for king antipas.
你的地位要依靠我的支持
Your position is reliant on my endorsement.
约翰  我的灵魂深处也贫穷和苦难
John, I'm poor and sick in my soul.
我很高兴能把这块地给你们
I'm glad to give you this land.
巴拿巴  完美至极
Barnabas, it's perfect.
神对每个人都有他的旨意  我意在布道
God has a purpose for each of us. I'm meant to preach.
要有耐心  司提反  时机将到
Be patient, Stephen. The time will come.
耶稣难道没说过
And didn't Jesus say,
"我会铲平这座圣殿  在三天内重建"
"I will rebuild this temple in three days"
就在被你处死后复生之前
Before he rose from the death you condemned him to?
让他闭嘴  让他闭嘴
Silence him. Shut him up.
耶稣啊  接受我的灵
Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.
"你的国将不再有暴力的消息
"No longer will violence be heard in your lands,
"你的地也不会有破坏和毁灭
"nor ruin and destruction within your borders.
"你的墙
"your walls
"应被称为救赎
"shall be called salvation,
"你的门都祈祷
"and your gates praise.
"你的昼
"No longer will the sun
"不再有日光照耀
"light your days
"你的夜不再有月光点亮
"nor the moon bright your night.
"你将获得主的永恒光芒
"You will have the lord for everlasting light
"和你神赐的天福"
"and your god for your glory."
我儿子死了  司提反死了
My son is dead! Stephen is dead!
是因为你  你和你的政治
Because of you! You and your politics!
他在哪
Where is he?
你的那个弥赛亚  他现在在哪
Where is he now, this Messiah of yours?
他为什么不复活他
Why doesn't he raise him up
或让那个主把司提反带回我们身边
or ask the Lord to bring Stephen back to us?
我们有资格试验他吗
Is it for us to test him?
我昨晚梦到
I dreamt last night
司提反不是最后一个死亡的
that Stephen wouldn't be the last of us to die.
另一个饥饿的灵魂听到了布道
Another hungry soul that's heard the word.
主与你同在
God be with you.
你是来听耶稣的布道的吗
Have you come to hear the word of Jesus?
不
No.
我叫扫罗
I am saul.
学者  犹太人  罗马公民  法利赛教徒
Scholar, Jew, Roman citizen, Pharisee,
耶路撒冷大圣殿的护卫
defender of the great temple of Jerusalem.
我来让你们看看
I have come to teach you of the wrath
你们如果不停止亵渎神明的行为
you will all bring down upon yourselves
会给自己带来怎样的惩罚
if you do not end your blasphemy.
如果
If.
荒漠和干渴的土地会喜悦
The desert and the parched land will be glad.
荒野会欢欣
The wilderness will rejoice...
绽放花朵
and blossom.
想番红花一样
Like the crocus,
绽开花朵
It will burst into bloom.
它会极尽欢欣
It will rejoice greatly...
大声欢呼
...and shout for joy.
所以  告诉我们
So, tell us,
我们的信仰怎么会如此错误
how are we so wrong in our belief?
朋友  跟我们说句话
Friend, speak with us.
你怎么了  没有舌头吗
What's the matter, have you no tongue?
还是没有脑子
Or no brain?
拿撒勒的耶稣
Jesus of Nazareth,
你们爱戴和歌颂的这个乡下弥赛亚
this peasant Messiah you love and praise,
不过是一个假先知
is nothing more than a false prophet.
你居然有胆量来这说出这种言辞
You dare come here and say that?
不是我说的  公会这么说
I don't say it. The Sanhedrin says it.
所罗门的诗篇上这么说
The psalms of Solomon say it.
耶利米  以赛亚和丹尼尔的预言都这么说
The prophecies of Jeremiah, Isaiah, and Daniel say it.
你又有何资格唱反调
Who are you to say otherwise?
有何资格
Who?
怎么了
What's the matter?
没有舌头吗
Have you no tongue?
还是没勇气说了
No courage?
走吧  小个子
Be gone, little man.
我真不明白你怎么想的  约拿单
I don't understand you, Jonathan.
你看到了这些屠杀  一波波酷刑
You saw the slaughter, the wave of crucifixions,
你看到耶路撒冷已被混乱占据
saw what bloody turmoil made its home in Jerusalem.
当然  父亲  我的眼睛很好
Of course. Father, I'm not blind.
你还容忍了该亚法  以大祭司的身份
And you accept that Caiaphas, as high priest,
染上这些血债
stands knee-deep in blood.
死亡是借罗马强兵之权的彼拉多带来的
Blood spilled by Pilate wielding the power of Rome.
是的  我也承认该亚法的处理有失
Yes, I accept Caiaphas has not handled things well.
那你为什么不同意换掉他呢
So, why can't you accept that he must be replaced?
耶路撒冷需要一个
Jerusalem needs a man who will forge
能改变和罗马人关系的人
a different relationship with Rome
带我们回到以前该亚法带来的
to take us back to the peaceful times
和平时代
Caiaphas once stood for.
公会期待能有人站出来挑战该亚法
The Sanhedrin is looking for a man to challenge Caiaphas.
亚那家族
The Annas family
希望你可以当此重任
needs that man to be you.
你可爱的家族
The whole idea of your loving family
要挤在我们的家里致谢的事
gathered in our house to give thanks
让我寝食不安
gives me indigestion.
那喝一剂药醒醒神吧
Well, take a potion. Clear your head.
两位贵客不请自来了
Two guests of honor have invited themselves.
能提前通知一下就更好了
Although a little more notice wouldn't have hurt.
安提帕斯和希罗底
Antipas and Herodias.
我都不知道拿撒勒人的营地
I had no idea the Nazarene camp
已经离城市如此近了
was so close to the city.
而且声势浩大
And so populated.
为什么会有人抛弃自己熟知的一切
Why would anyone leave everything they knew
去过这种日子
to live like that?
普林节之际大家能光临寒舍
We are honored the festival of purim
是我们莫大的荣幸
has brought you to our home.
其实  这也是个来耶路撒冷的好借口
In truth, it was a useful excuse to come to Jerusalem.
为了来看看它是否还屹立于此
To see if the city was still standing.
我儿子和我认为
My son and I think,
作为犹太人  我们该谈谈最近的黑暗时期
as Jews, we can talk honestly about recent dark days.
人民不会很快淡忘那些死在
The people will not soon forget the blood spilled
彼拉多总督酷刑下的亡灵
in governor Pilate's wave of crucifixions.
他们也不该忘记
They shouldn't forget.
但人民何时又曾满意过呢
But was there ever a time when the people were content?
如果人民的怒火可以消去
If the anger of the people was fading,
你大可如此沾沾自喜
there would be room for this complacent approach.
父亲  我们并没有自满
Father, we are hardly complacent.
但人民的怒火愈燃愈旺
But the anger is growing,
随着城外沙漠上的流动城市愈发壮大
just as the new city of tents out in the desert is growing.
你是说营地吗
You mean the camp?
现在都有上千个了
There are thousands there now.
没错
Yes.
来的路上我们路过了那里
We passed it on our way here.
它会发展成什么样
Where will it stop?
五千追随者吗
At 5,000 converts?
或者十万
100,000?
大家能不能别再谈
Will everybody please stop
这些人了
going on about these people?
告诉我  你到底想让我怎么做
Tell me, what exactly is it that you'd have me do?
去他们的帐篷里直接杀掉他们吗
Have them slaughtered in their tents?
安提帕斯  当然  这些百姓
Antipas, surely, the people --
还有你  他们的统治者
and you, as their ruler --
都希望有个能管事的大祭司
want to see a High Priest in control of events.
而不是由他们领导
Not led by them.
不是任罗马总督随心所欲地支配
Not governed by the whim of his Roman master.
我很喜欢这种叛变的味道
I do enjoy the smell of treachery.
可怜的该亚法就像
Poor old Caiaphas has the look of a man
一个行将赴死的人
preparing to face the executioner.
如果要在他
If it was a choice
和年轻的约拿单中选一个做大祭司
between him and young Jonathan as High Priest,
我都不知道该选哪个
I don't know who I'd go for.
都别选
Neither.
但我必须支持一个
But I'll have to give my support to one of them,
然后让彼拉多来决定
and then let Pilate have the responsibility.
女士
My lady.
然后是别是巴的撒迦利亚
And then there was Zachary of Beersheba,
一个让热情冲昏了头脑的人
a passionate man who tried to follow
他想要效仿摩西
the example of Moses
于是带领他的弟兄穿越红海
and lead his friends across the Red Sea.
他溺水死了  他们都死了
He drowned, and so did they.
还有比利亚的西门
And then there was Simon from Peraea --
勇敢多谋的西门
brave, well-intentioned Simon.
他自以为由上帝差来
Well, he believed that he was sent by God
但只是让犹太人的生活更
but only made a Jew's life ha--
但只是让犹太人在罗马统治下的生活更艰难
but only made a Jew's life harder under Rome.
另外还有个冒牌货
And there was another pretender --
来自加利利的骗子
an imposter from Galilee,
耶稣
this man Jesus.
你是彼得  我听过你传道
You're Peter. I've heard you preach.
讲得不错
You do it well.
或许有点过于动情了  但
A little softhearted, perhaps, but...
我可以举个例子来击破你那虚假的弥赛亚
I have a case to make against your false Messiah!
你愿意听吗  彼得
Do you want to hear it, Peter,
还是害怕我当着这些蒙昧的群众
or are you afraid I will unpick your delusions
揭穿你的诡诈之言
in front of this gullible crowd?
这个人生活在黑暗中
This man is living in darkness
甚至不知道自己的双眼已被蒙蔽
and doesn't even know his eyes are closed.
他自称知晓这些
He claims such knowledge,
但也不过是在黑夜中蹒跚
but he's just stumbling in the dark
如果没有意识到这点
if he doesn't know this --
若不籍著耶稣
no one can come to the Father
没有人能到天父那里去
except through Jesus.
耶稣就是道路
Jesus is the way
真理  生命
and the truth and the life.
你们的耶稣
This Jesus of yours
被这些文盲渔夫奉为先知
is nothing more than a false prophet
不过是个冒牌货
of illiterate fishermen.
你们全被他投入了谎言的罗网中
He has you all in a net of lies.
约翰
John!
你对待自己的言语
You use words
就如商人对待卖出的石头
like a trader selling stones.
这当中没有真心  没有爱
There's no heart to them, no love.
我有  爱
I have...love
对你想毁掉的那些东西
for those things you want to destroy --
耶路撒冷中心的圣殿
the temple in the heart of Jerusalem,
几个世纪的律法与传统
centuries of law and tradition.
你那可悲的小团体
Your pathetic little band can no more replace
不过是鞋里的小跳蚤
than a flea can fill the shoes of a man.
简单来说
Speak simply.
哪怕你的思想中有一点真理
If there is truth to your thoughts,
人们都会理解你
you'll be understood.
我就说个简单的真理
Here's a simple truth --
如果要与圣殿为敌
if you set yourself against the temple,
你必将为圣殿所毁
you will be destroyed by the temple.
简单明了的
Simple.
真理
Truth.
就算我能说服公会
Even if I could persuade the Sanhedrin
信任你们的家族
to trust your family,
谁又能对越来越多的同胞
Who stood by while more and more
被钉死在十字架上视若无睹
of our people were crucified.
-并没有...  -就算我愿意
- There was nothing -- - And even if I was willing to speak
为你们辩解  为你们争取到
in your defense and so gain for you
足以推翻该亚法的支持者
the support you'll need to unseat Caiaphas
并弥补由你们所造成的伤害
and heal the wounds you've caused,
你就不为
have you no shame
密谋推翻自己女婿的行为感到羞耻吗
that you'd plot against your own son-in-law?
我很羞耻
I have shame.
羞耻于我没能尽早行动
Shame that I didn't act sooner
挽救那些身处水火之中的人们
to save so many from their pain.
那些不幸身亡和像你一样的人们
Those who died and those, like you,
那些失去挚爱的人们
who lost the ones they loved.
我们请求你不要让那失败
We ask you to not let that failing
带来更多的鲜血和折磨
cost more blood and suffering,
在我们重新开始时  不让那些时刻被遗忘
not to let the moment pass when we can act to start afresh.
我儿子约拿单是个正直的人
My son Jonathan is a man of integrity
会真心实意地传达耶路撒冷人民的心声
who will truly speak for the people of Jerusalem.
他是唯一一个能带来这两样...
The only man who can bring both --
变革和延续的人
both change and continuity.
在你向彼拉多提出这个提议之前
Before you even think of making the case to Pilate,
他需要安提帕斯毫无保留的支持
He'll need the unreserved backing of Antipas.
彼拉多会想要他的批准来维持秩序
Pilate will want his approval to maintain order.
如果有了你的支持
If, with your support,
我们能够将公会的人团结起来
we can unite the Sanhedrin behind us,
我们今天就能去找安提帕斯
we can approach Antipas today.
我保证  你不会后悔的
You won't regret this, I promise.
这个男人会让你们相信
This man would have you believe
一个被钉死的弥赛亚
in a crucified Messiah.
《申命记》中写到
Deuteronomy says,
"凡是吊死于树上或是十字架的人
"For he that is hanged on a tree or on a cross
均遭上帝诅咒"
is accursed of God."
但上帝令他复活
But God raised him up,
将他从死亡中解脱出来
having loosed him from the pains of death
因为他不会为死亡所困
because it was not possible he should be held by it.
这是你的说法
So you claim,
但你们之中有谁亲眼见到了复生
but who among you has seen the resurrection?
谁
Who?
你看见了吗
You?
你呢  你呢
You? You?
只有这个需要你们相信这个故事的骗子
Only your charlatans, who need you to believe it.
耶稣和他的话备受爱戴
Jesus and the truth of his message are loved.
被我们所有的同胞爱戴吗
By all our people?
连耶路撒冷人都不尽全信
Not even by all of Jerusalem.
他们对他的爱戴如此至少
They loved him so little...
甚至处死了他
they executed him.
实现了以赛亚的预言
And fulfilled Isaiah's prophecy.
弥赛亚是一个
The Messiah is a man
不幸的  深知惨痛的男人
of sorrows and acquainted with grief.
这个人认为你们的挚爱被处决
This man thinks it's a mark of success
是成功的象征
when those you love are executed.
你们都死光了他才会开心
He won't be happy until you're all dead...
就像司提反
Like Stephen.
你要是再待在这里
If you stay here one moment longer,
我发誓  我会拔下你的头
I swear I'm going to tear your head off.
别担心
Don't worry.
我已经听到足够多的话
I've heard enough to see
让我明白你们不会放弃这种错觉的理由
that reason won't break you from your delusions.
但你们还会再见到我
You will see me again, though.
我保证
Be sure of that.
迦玛列拉比
Rabbi Gamaliel,
这些沙漠中的渎神者
how can these blasphemers in the desert
为什么会想要结束这一切
want to end all this?
不要关心他们的事
Don't concern yourself with them.
管好你自己的学习吧
Look to your own studies.
提高自己的理解力  然后...
Improve your understanding, and then --
我知道  但他们就是看不到
Yes, but they just don't see
这些...所有这些
that this -- all of this --
正是耶路撒冷的心脏和灵魂
is the heart and soul of Jerusalem.
我想告诉他们  但他们不肯讲道理
I tried to tell them, but they just won't see reason.
那么  扫罗  不要再把你的时间
Then, Saul, don't spend more of your energy
浪费在纠正他们的错误上
trying to correct their mistake.
我看到了你的前途  从学者到拉比
I see a path for you from scholar to Rabbi,
也许还会从拉比
from Rabbi to, perhaps,
变成公会的一员
a seat on the Sanhedrin.
谁知道呢
Who knows?
这些人
These men,
跟公会做的是一样的事
they do the same work as the Sanhedrin.
辛勤工作着  为了保留旧的传统
They toil to preserve the old
使它保持活力
while making it new.
而这个渔夫彼得和其他人想做的
What this fisherman Peter and the others want to do
却是毁灭传统
is destroy the old,
用新的一套来代替它
replace it with the new.
我必须想出办法来阻止他们
I have to find a way to stop them.
我必须这么做
I have to.
我觉得事情进展顺利
I think that went well.
给您
For you.
周年纪念礼物
An anniversary gift.
在你离开我们家之后
After you left our house,
我妻子提醒我  正是在十年前的普珥日
my wife reminded me that it was at Purim 10 years ago
我们第一次相见
that we first met.
我作为大祭司
Me as High Priest,
你作为加利利和比利亚的分封王
you as Tetrarch of Galilee and Perea.
我们都想把对方除掉
Each trying to work the other out.
而到了今天  我们也仍然在这么做
And here we are, still trying.
请吧
Please.
那么  你的岳父和他的儿子
So, your father-in-law and his son
很想从你这里抢走
would very much like to take from you
你所穿戴的高贵的祭司袍
those fine robes of office that you wear.
那么
Now...
你打算如何处置
What are you going to do
这些沙漠中的狂热之徒呢
about these fanatics in the desert?
这场狂热崇拜的主谋  他们跟随的头目
The ringleader of the cult, the man they follow,
是加利利人
is from Galilee.
这对我的形象影响十分恶劣
This reflects very badly on me.
他们很快就会对于跟随他们的弥赛亚
They will soon tire of the hardships
所带来的苦难而感到厌倦的
that come from following their... Messiah.
但那样又能如何呢
But what happens?
异议成了造反
Dissent becomes revolt.
罗马的应对将会带来毁灭
The Roman response could be devastating.
为我解决这个麻烦  该亚法
Solve this problem for me, Caiaphas.
如果这场推翻你的密谋呈到彼拉多那里
And if this attempt to overthrow you reaches Pilate,
我会支持你
you will have my support.
我们知道你在跟我父亲和我哥哥
We know you're conspiring
密谋些什么事
with my father and brother.
我不懂你在说什么呢
Should I know what you're talking about?
这场战斗  你们三个是赢不了的
The three of you won't win this fight.
我丈夫仍然会继续做大祭司
My husband will remain in office as high priest,
而你们则会因背叛遭到报应
and you will suffer for your betrayal.
你丈夫已经失势了
Tide is turning against your husband,
我也无法阻止时局
and I can't stand in the way of it.
如果你们意识不到这一点
If you don't recognize that,
你们都将被滔滔洪水所淹没
you'll both drown in the flood.
大祭司今天还有更多的事要做
The High Priest has more to deal with today
比你想象得要多
than you can even imagine.
而你却认为我应该把他
And you think that I should bring him
-带来这里见你  -是的
- out here to talk to you? - Yes.
三天后再来
Come back in three days.
你得到的回复还会是一样
The answer will still be the same,
但至少我有足够的时间忘记你
but at least it'll give me chance to forget you.
三天后  圣殿很可能会面临加倍的危险
In three days, the danger to the temple could be doubled.
圣殿会有什么危险
What danger to the temple?
原谅我  我
Forgive me. I...
我只是在说沙漠里聚集的那些
I was merely talking about the followers of the false Messiah
伪弥赛亚的门徒
gathering in the desert.
跟我来
Come with me.
听说你想要见我
You wanted to see me?
谢谢您的恩典
Thank you for your good grace.
我在圣殿档案馆读到过很多
Having read much in the temple archives
您家族的伟大历史
of your family's great history,
我满怀着敬意  希望
I hope that, with respect --
我们可以少一些繁文缛节吗
Could we perhaps have a little less respect?
-时间紧迫  -当然
- Time kills us all. - Of course.
我相信我们有着共同的兴趣
I believe we share a common interest,
共同的愿望
a common desire
想要把某群害虫赶出耶路撒冷
to rid Jerusalem of a pest --
那些渔夫和他们的追随者
the fishermen and their followers
在城外的势力和自信心
growing in numbers and confidence
日益膨胀
outside the city walls.
你为什么会希望他们离开
And what is it that fuels your desire to see them gone?
他们令我感到厌恶
They offend me.
他们想要破坏圣殿
Their actions to undermine the temple,
他们的挑衅行为激怒了我
their defiance offends me.
他们公然反抗公会
Their defiance of the Sanhedrin,
即使公会已经
who could not have been more
非常明确地裁决...
definitive in their verdict when they said --
你到底想要我怎么样
What exactly do you want?
我希望您能授权我
The authority to...
代表您
act on your behalf
来解决这个问题
and solve this problem --
彻底赶走这些亵渎者
to remove these blasphemers so completely
不让其留下一丁点儿蛛丝马迹
that not even the stain of their memory is left behind.
我一直在想着司提反
I just can't stop thinking about Stephen.
不要再这样了
Stop being such a man.
什么
What?
你看见了葬礼上的女人
You see the women at the funeral.
她们哭泣哀号
They weep and they wail
把痛苦全都发泄出来
and they scream out their pain
那样全世界就了解她们的悲痛
so the whole world knows about it.
而当女人不加掩饰的悲痛散播开来时
And while all this openhearted grieving goes on,
男人却都都低垂眉目
the men look at their feet
只摆出悲伤的表情
and put on their sad face.
不要闷在心里
Don't bottle it up.
释放你的痛苦
Let out that pain.
引领我们  以此来纪念司提反  彼得
Honor Stephen by leading us, Peter.
我需要您给予我
What I need is for you to give me the authority
最低级别圣殿守卫所拥有的权限
you would give the least promoted of your temple guard.
你要如何使用这一权限
Authority to use how?
给我配备20个圣殿守卫
And 20 men from that guard.
他们的力量在于其群众基础
Their strength is their popularity.
我要破坏掉他们的群众基础
I want to take that from them.
你们都有疑惑
You have questions.
你们说  "为什么他称我为他的磐石"
You say, "Why did he call me his rock?"
你们问  "我是他的基石吗
You ask, "Am I the foundation?
他的教会将会建造在这里吗"
Is this where his church will be built?"
只有一个基石
There is only one foundation stone.
他的名字就是耶稣基督
And his name is Jesus Christ!
而他的教会也不是这里
And his church is not here.
既不在这营帐 亦或那石墙中
It's not in those tents or these walls.
而在你们所有人心中
It's you -- all of you.
你们就是他的教会
You are his church.
就像那些虽未亲见耶稣复活
And like those we asked to believe
却响应我们  皈依天主的人一样
even though they didn't see him rise again,
我们必须抛却畏惧
we must push away our fear
哪怕要为此遭受迫害
even as we recognize the persecution we face.
我们必须去耶路撒冷
We have to go to Jerusalem
广布真言
and preach the word
建立他的教会
to build his church!
人你自己去招
Recruit your own men.
钱我出
I'll pay.
恕我直言
Forgive me,
如果人们看见是您出手
but wouldn't it benefit your authority
不正有利于您巩固地位吗
to be seen as the hand at work?
我们必须从神殿长老和他们罗马主子那儿
We need to claim back the true message of our faith
夺回我们信仰真谛的解释权
from the families of the temple and their masters from Rome.
他们杀掉了那个说过此话的人
They crucified the man who said to you,
"我是世界的光
"I am the light of the world.
跟从我的  就不在黑暗里走"
Whoever follows me won't walk in darkness."
而我  亲眼见到了他
And with my own eyes, I saw him.
我们刚刚埋葬了一个好人  一位挚友
We just buried a man -- a good man and a friend.
就因为他敢于说出真相  就遭石刑而死
Stoned to death because he dared speak the truth.
他和你们一样  都很年轻
He was a young man, like you.
他像你们一样  流了血  受了苦
He shed blood and felt pain, just like you.
像你们一样  他的母亲为他落泪
His mother wept tears for him, just as yours would.
但他仍无所畏惧地大声说出天主的真言
But he had a burning need to speak the truth of the word of god.
奉大祭司该亚法之命
With the authority of high priest Caiaphas,
我乃是大数人扫罗
I, Saul of Tarsus,
指控在场所有人等支持渎神谬论
hereby accuse all the people here of supporting blasphemy!
你们可看见了
Do you see this?
这些罗马人的奴仆对我们大加迫害
These friends of Rome standing against us?
这就是你的回应吗  诉诸暴力
Is this your answer? Violence?
你小看我了
You underestimate me.
你们将被统统拿下
You will all be taken away
你们的名字将会与罪犯并列
and your name added to a list of offenders!
这些人并未犯下什么罪过
These people have done nothing.
若再敢触犯法律
Any further offense,
你们将接受公会审判
and you will all face the Sanhedrin Court!
那便拿了我们  羞辱我们吧
Then take us. Take our names.
你该拿的是我们
We're the ones to arrest.
不  我放你们走
No. You two can go.
平民很快就会知道与你们为伍有多危险
These people will soon learn the danger of your company.
你和你的手下
You and your men are no match
是无法与圣灵赋予我们的火焰相抗衡的
for the fire of the holy spirit that fills us.
是么
Really?
那便看看是谁火光更亮
Well, let's see whose fire burns brightest, shall we?
给我拿了
Take them!
使人民疏远那些狂热分子就是削弱他们
I've weakened these fanatics by isolating them,
让他们的支持者反戈相向
by turning their supporters against them.
你是说恐吓耶路撒冷的城民么
By terrorizing the citizens of Jerusalem.
这个问题本来也无人能解
Well, there was a problem nobody seemed able to solve.
但你也没解成
Neither have you.
他们知道若是在耶路撒冷城内
They know you'll persecute them
听那些布道者布道便会被你逮捕
if they listen to the preachers in Jerusalem,
所以他们离开耶路撒冷
so they're leaving the city
去听那些人的布道
to hear what they have to say.
你不会真以为这个扫罗
Did you really think this man Saul
会妨碍我们的使命吧
would stand in the way of our mission?
神殿方面是不会坐视的
The temple won't stand for this.
用不了多久他们定会出手阻拦
They won't let it go on much longer.
看来你的勇士扫罗
It looks like your hero Saul
对拿撒勒人追随者的营地也奈何不得
couldn't solve the problem of the Nazarene camp.
另外两名同谋呢
Where are the other two conspirators?
我不是来争吵的
I didn't come to bicker.
我来是请你自重一点
I came to ask you to show some dignity,
看清楚公会已经
to recognize that the will of the Sanhedrin
不再支持你了
is turning against you,
我来是想请你为了家族的利益
and ask you, for the good of this family,
主动让位吧
to stand down.
为了家族的利益吗
For the good of this family?
为了家族的利益
For the good of this family,
你当年做大祭司的时候
you, who in his day as High Priest
不懂得与罗马保持步调一致
hadn't the wits to walk in step with Rome.
留下了一堆烂摊子让我来收拾
You, who left a mess behind him that I had to clear up.
如今你却又要密谋反对我了吗
You plot against me?
如今我倒要在这里听
And now I must listen to the rantings
一个失败的刻薄老头在这里吼叫什么
of a failed and a bitter old man
以家族的利益为重吗
for the good of this family?
从我家滚出去
Get out of my house!
趁我还没有忘记你是我妻子的父亲
Before I forget you're my wife's father
并将刀插入你的胸前
and put a blade between your ribs.
这事我们去找彼拉多评判
We'll take this to Pilate.
你必须支持该亚法而非他的妻弟
You must favor Caiaphas over his brother-in-law.
我必须吗
Must I?
不用你教我怎么做
Don't tell me what to do.
十年的盟友
A 10-year-old alliance
不能无故抛弃
shouldn't be tossed aside without good cause.
你支持的是该亚法还是他的妻子
Is it Caiaphas you approve of or his wife?
我听说你们两个现在成好朋友了
I hear the two of you are becoming the best of friends.
弥涅耳瓦  智慧女神
Minerva, goddess of wisdom.
弥涅耳瓦
Minerva,
他们中谁应该做大祭司
which of these men shall be High Priest,
谁又应该被抛弃在沙漠中腐烂
and which one shall be left to rot in the desert?
没有答复
Nothing.
太令人失望了
Very disappointing.
有传言说
There is a rumor
您事先知道有人想密谋加害我却袖手旁观
you knew of the plot against my life and did nothing.
是真的吗
Is that true?
不  太荒唐了
No. That's ridiculous.
还有传言说您在我的宫殿里安插了眼线
And a rumor you have a spy here in my palace.
更有传言说您每晚都去拿撒勒人的营地
And another that you visit the Nazarene's camp each night
并与他们一同祷告
and pray with them.
有人建议  这一切都表明
All of which, it's been suggested,
您不再适任此职
makes you unfit to continue in office.
这些传言是真的吗
Is any of this true?
全都不是
None of it.
这些都是想要污蔑我名誉的人传播的谎言
Lies are being spread by those who wish to undermine me.
你声名扫地是因为你自己没有抓住...
You undermine yourself by failing to get a grip on --
够了
Enough.
我可不会把我的时间浪费在
I will not waste my time
像母亲解决孩子间的口角那样
separating truth from fiction,
分辨虚实上
like a mother with squabbling children.
当时硬币上印有罗马帝国皇帝的头像
让提庇留来判定吧
Tiberius shall decide.
我遇到过一个希腊人  每一个决定
I met a Greek once who made every decision
都靠抛硬币
with the toss of a coin.
皇帝的头像
Emperor's head...
硬币另一面是提庇留的母亲
还是神圣的莉薇娅
Or the divine Livia?
我该嘉奖你的抱负
Shall I commend you for your ambition?
还是因你传播毫无根据的谣言而谴责你
Or do I condemn you for spreading baseless rumors?
若是头像  我谴责你
Heads, I condemn.
若是莉薇娅  我嘉奖你
Livia, I commend.
是头像
Heads.
所以我因你那拙劣的背叛
Then I condemn you
而谴责你
for making such a poor job of your treachery.
那些渔夫和他们的追随者们
These fishermen and their followers --
处理了吗
Are they being dealt with?
处理了  都妥善彻底地处理了
They are, firmly and finally.
大祭司的工作并不难
Unless he wants to be loved by all,
只要他不要妄想受所有人的爱戴
the High Priest's job is not a hard one.
他必须满足罗马帝国对犹太行省的期望
He must deliver what's expected of the province of Judea by Rome
并压制他的子民那诸多而且通常无理的要求
and resist the many, often irrational, demands of his people.
厨房里的姑娘们都能做到
There are girls in the kitchen who can do that.
路边的野狗也能做到
Dogs in the street.
甚至驴都能做到
Even a donkey.
如果是头像  你留下
Heads, you stay.
如果是莉薇娅...
Livia...
我就拉一头驴子来取代你
I'll replace you with a donkey.
该亚法  请您把它捡起来  好吗
Get that, will you, Caiaphas?
是头像
Head.
很好
Excellent.
你们两个可以走了
You both may go.
我需要和你们的大祭司谈谈
I need to speak with your High Priest.
吸取教训吧
And the lesson is,
如果你不擅长玩弄权术  就别自取其辱
don't play politics unless you're good at it.
这枚硬币...
This coin...
两面都是皇帝的头像
It has two heads.
没错  是吧
It does, doesn't it?
奉依然担任大祭司的该亚法之命
By order of Caiaphas, who remains High Priest,
你们被从公会除名了
you are removed from the Sanhedrin.
即使是你的父兄
Even though it was your own father and brother
也不放过吗
who hatched this plot?
你们必须离开耶路撒冷
And you will leave Jerusalem
否则我将以叛国罪逮捕你们
or find yourself arrested for treason.
这一切
This all began
都始于对拿撒勒人  耶稣的谋害
with the murder of the Nazarene -- Jesus.
你们所有的干预  你们的诡计
All your interfering, your scheming.
总有一天  会让你们万劫不复
It will bring you down... eventually.
我试着和他们讲道理
I tried to reason with them,
但他们就是听不进去
but they just wouldn't listen.
我试图离间他们和他们的支持者
I tried to come between them and their supporters,
但显然他们更倾向于
but it would appear they would prefer
拿撒勒人那愚蠢的教义
the idiotic doctrine of the Nazarene.
我以此全权委任你去解决他们
This gives you my full authority to rid me of them.
彻底解决
Permanently.
不择手段
Do whatever is necessary.
Whatever is necessary.
让我来告诉你们他们是些什么样的人
Let me tell you about these people.
这些人
These people
意图摧毁圣殿...
want to bring down the temple --
圣殿
The temple.
指引着你我人生的方向
The guiding hand in yours and my life.
是智慧的源泉
The well of wisdom.
而他们却认为没有人
And they think nobody --
没有人  可以阻挡他们
nobody -- will stand in their way.
他们藐视公会的统治
They disregard the ruling of the Sanhedrin,
公会宣布他们为渎神者
who call them blasphemers!
而第二天
The very next day,
他们中的一人却又走进圣殿
one of them walked into the temple itself
大肆宣扬他的亵渎
proclaiming his profanity.
尽管...
And although --
尽管耶路撒冷的人民
and although the people of Jerusalem
进行了审判  用石刑处死了他
delivered their justice and they stoned him to death,
他们仍继续招募那些易轻信的
they continue recruiting the gullible
还有意志不坚的人投身他们的事业
and the weak-minded to their cause.
我们受够了吗
Do we say enough?
受够了
Enough!
我们应该让他们头破血流吗
Will we break their heads?
有了剑
With swords
有棍子  有拳头
and clubs and bare fists,
我们就可以说  "离开这片土地
we will say, "Leave this land,
否则你们就会
or you will leave this earth
躺在裹尸布中离开"
in a shroud of blood!"
拿上武器  穿上盔甲
Grab weapons! Grab armor!
跟我走
Follow me!
在场的人听好  把话传出去
Pay heed to this and spread the word.
这些人被逮捕是因为他们为假弥赛亚的信徒们
These people are being arrested for aiding, sheltering,
提供帮助  住所和食物
and feeding the followers of the false Messiah.
他们将会被...
They will be...
他们将会被囚禁
they will be imprisoned.
其他效仿者
Anyone else who does likewise
也会被收监关押
will also pay with their freedom.
不要妄想逃到沙漠里
And don't think of scurrying off to the desert
向你们的朋友们寻求帮助
for help from your friends.
马上就要轮到他们了
It's their turn next.
他来了
He's coming!
扫罗回来了
Saul's coming back!
他带来了军队
He's bringing men with swords.
只拿随身物品快跑
Take what you can!
快帮大家离开
Let's get everyone out of here.
这边  走  跟他们走
This way. Go. Go with them.
我们应该回加利利去
We should go back to Galilee.
不  我们必须团结在一起
No, we have to stay together.
我们到耶路撒冷再见
We gather again in Jerusalem.
我们得走了
We have to go now.
不  我留下
No. I'll stay.
我不会被他的威胁和恐吓所吓倒
I will not be cowed by this man and his threats.
我不能留你独自一人面对他
I won't leave you to face him alone.
他不是一个人
He won't be alone.
这是我的土地  我不会走的
This was my land. I'm staying.
我也是
And me.
迎客之道千千万
There's more than one way to welcome a visitor.
耶路撒冷再见
See you in Jerusalem.
赶快  快跑
Please hurry. Run.
小心混合
Mix it carefully.
太多就不起作用了
Too much and it won't work.
快走  动作快点
Go. Move faster.
快走  快点
Go on. Faster.
拉住我的手
Take my hand.
雅各  快走
James, go.
全部推倒
Pull it all down.
烧掉
Burn it.
我不想看到他们留下的任何痕迹
I want nothing left to show that they were ever here.
立刻
Now!
他再不走就来不及了
He's leaving it too late.
不
No.
他知道自己在干什么
He knows what he's doing.
抓住他
Take him!
我们看看谁的火烧得更旺
Let's see whose fire burns brightest now!
不
No!
不要
No!!
我要杀了你
I will crush you!
你有本事就来试试
You will try!